<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Ruslan Kishai</title>
        <link>https://kishai.codes/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Ruslan Kishai</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>Ruslan Kishai</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kishai.codes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Simplicity of Burnout</title>
        <link>https://kishai.codes/post/the-simplicity-of-burnout/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://kishai.codes/post/the-simplicity-of-burnout/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-beginning-expectations-vs-reality&#34;&gt;The Beginning: Expectations vs. Reality
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;It might sound ironic that, after years of starting and abandoning new blog ideas, I’ve finally committed to writing my first post — and it’s about burnout. This article is a self-reflection on the factors that brought me to this place and my plans to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s rewind a bit. It’s 2020, and I’m working at a large company. The experience wasn’t quite what I’d expected. Despite building the project from scratch, we relied on outdated practices. My lead didn’t seem to have much more experience than I did — at least, that’s how it felt back then. When COVID hit and we shifted to working from home, my focus gradually drifted from career to family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-shift-finding-balance-losing-purpose&#34;&gt;The Shift: Finding Balance, Losing Purpose
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I moved to a different company, and my workaholic habits started to fade. I settled into a routine where I worked strictly during office hours. Over time, I introduced new architecture and automation solutions that eased my workload. The job became almost effortless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ve found work-life balance and time for yourself,” you might say. But there was a crucial flaw in this setup that I didn’t see at first — and only recently understood. Simplicity and monotony can lead to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may sound obvious, but over the past four years, I truly believed I’d hit the jackpot — a dream company. For the last two of those years, however, I stagnated. The ease and routine had quietly eroded my passion, leaving me feeling uninspired and burned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-spark-challenging-myself-to-grow&#34;&gt;The Spark: Challenging Myself to Grow
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, how did I find joy in programming again? I started seeking out projects, tasks, or side work that would push me technically and creatively. Experimenting with unfamiliar technologies and trying out a complex side project gave me back some of the challenge I had been missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting specific goals for learning new frameworks, design patterns, or even revisiting advanced concepts helped me stay engaged. I enrolled in online courses and joined study groups to keep myself motivated and excited about upcoming industry trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While burnout can be isolating, connecting with other developers reminded me why I loved programming in the first place. Joining communities and attending meetups helped me stay inspired and brought a much-needed social component back into my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also took some time to revisit why I entered the field in the first place. Reconnecting with that purpose helped me frame my work in a broader context, making it feel meaningful even if individual tasks didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-moving-forward&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Moving Forward
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Handling burnout wasn’t an overnight fix, but these strategies gradually helped me rediscover joy in programming. Developer burnout is a real challenge, but by identifying what’s missing — be it challenge, community, or purpose — and intentionally reintroducing those elements, we can create a more fulfilling career path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
